<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of Alexander Fraiser of Doores, Knight and baronet, principal physician to the King of Great Britain &amp;c. who died at Whitehall, April 28, 1681, in the seventieth and fifth year of his age, and was solemnly interr'd amongst his ancestors at Doores the 28 of July following / by John Menzies.</title>
            <author>Menzeis, John, 1624-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50625</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1728</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28826</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10763489</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10763489</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45736</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50625)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45736)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1406:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the funeral of Alexander Fraiser of Doores, Knight and baronet, principal physician to the King of Great Britain &amp;c. who died at Whitehall, April 28, 1681, in the seventieth and fifth year of his age, and was solemnly interr'd amongst his ancestors at Doores the 28 of July following / by John Menzies.</title>
                  <author>Menzeis, John, 1624-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the heir of Andrew Anderson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fraizer, Alexander, --  Sir, 1610?-1681.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45736:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the Funeral OF S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> ALEXANDER FRAISER OF DOORES, Knight and Baronet, Principal Phyſician to the <hi>KING</hi> of <hi>Great-Britain,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Who died at <hi>Whitehall, April</hi> 28. 1681. In the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth and fifth year of his Age.</p>
            <p>And was Solemnly Interr'd amongſt his Anceſtors at <hi>DOORES</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. of <hi>July</hi> following.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN MENZIES,</hi> Profeſſor of Divinity in <hi>Aberdene.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by the Heir of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to his moſt Sacred Majeſty, <hi>Anno DOM.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:45736:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45736:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalm. 90.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>So teach us to number our dayes, that we may apply our heart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> wiſdom.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T's ſaid of <hi>Xerxes,</hi> viewing, from the top of an hill, his vaſt Army, conſiſting of no leſs then a Million of Men, he fell a weeping, that within the ſpace of an hundreth years, all theſe gallant perſons would be ſnatcht away by death; and in a much ſhorter time it came to paſs. All the uſe, that heathen Prince could make of this inevitable fate and mortality of Mankind, was to weep over it; But the holy Ghoſt in this Text, ſuggeſts a more profitable improvement thereof. <hi>So teach us to number our dayes, that we may apply our hearts unto wiſdom.</hi> Happy we, if by the work and exerciſe of this day, we be excited to learn this heavenly and divine Art.</p>
            <p>The Opinions of Interpreters have varied touching the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of this Pſalm. Holy <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his <hi>Enarration</hi> upon it, will not grant it to be Penned by <hi>Moſes,</hi> though the Inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on carry his Name; <hi>A prayer of Moſes the man of God.</hi> But S. <hi>Hierom, epiſt.</hi> 139. Unto <hi>Cyprian</hi> a Preſbyter, will not only have this Pſalm to be Compoſed by <hi>Moſes,</hi> but alſo, all that follow until the hundred. In aſcribing ſo many to <hi>Moſes, Hierom,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:45736:3"/>without all peradventure (with reverence be it ſpoken to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> great a Name) was miſtaken; for in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 99.6. Mention is made of <hi>Samuel,</hi> who was much poſterior to <hi>Moſes;</hi> and the <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95. is expreſly attributed unto <hi>David, Heb.</hi> 4.7. Yet the deſription of this Pſaſm giving it ſo diſtinctly to <hi>Moſes,</hi> I dare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bereave him of it. The occaſion whereof, is ſuppoſed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> heavy threatning, that all the men of War, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Egypt,</hi> from twenty years old and upwards, ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Wilderneſs, two only excepted, <hi>Joſhuah</hi> and <hi>Caleb. Moſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> therefore conſidering, that ſo many thouſands, yea, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of thouſands, ſhould be cut of in the ſpace of fourty years, Penned this Lecture of Mortality, to excite the People to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for their reprival, and to make a due improvement of the little time of reprival given to them. In the firſt eleven <hi>Verſes,</hi> he diſcourſes of mans Mortality, and the grand procuring cauſe thereof, namely Sin. From the twelfth <hi>Verſe</hi> to the end, he puts up fervent Supplications unto God. From which, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the main deſign of the whole Pſalm, it hath its Denominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>The Prayer of Moſes, the man of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To day, I have pitched on the firſt of theſe Petitions. Since it is ſo, that man is ſuch a poor mortal and frail Creature, <hi>So teach us, O Lord, to number our dayes, that we may apply our hearts unto wiſdom.</hi> The Verſion of this <hi>Verſe,</hi> as it runs in the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Latine, is ſo widely diſtant from the Hebrew, and ſo hard to be reduced to any tolerable ſenſe, that I judge it not worth the while, to trouble you therewith.</p>
            <p>In the Words, as they are reduced by our Tranſlators from the Original (with whom <hi>Pagnin,</hi> and <hi>Arrias Montanus,</hi> learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Romaniſts, leaving their vulgar Version, do agree) two things do chiefly offer themſelves to us; one is, the Pſalmiſts Petition, <hi>So teach us to number our dayes;</hi> the other is, the ſcope of his Petition, or the benefit that ſhould accrew, by the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of the mercy prayed for, <hi>that we may apply our hearts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45736:3"/>wiſdom:</hi> Or as it is varied on the Margin, <hi>that we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cauſe our hearts come unto wiſdom. Pagnin</hi> thus, <hi>&amp; adduce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus cor in ſapientiant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Petition at firſt view, may ſeem ſomewhat ſtrange, he had ſaid, <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>The dayes of our years are threeſcore years and ten, and if by reaſon of ſtrength, they be fourſcore years,</hi> now there needs no great Art to reckon up ſeventy or eighty. Surely therefore, ſomething more muſt be meant then the bare Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metical Calculation of the number of our years. And the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if the quality of the perſon be considered, who breathed forth the Petition, a man Learned in all the Wiſdom of the <hi>Egyptians, Act.</hi> 7.22. and ſo not meanly Verſed in the Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, theſe Sciences greatly flouriſhing in that Countrey, at that time. The myſteriouſneſs of the great Art, wherein the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt pleads to be inſtructed, ſeems to be insinuated, in the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifying Particle, <hi>SO, So teach us to number our dayes.</hi> The He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chen,</hi> is elſewhere rendred, right or well, <hi>Numb.</hi> 27.7. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 7.9. So that the Scope of the Words of the Text is, <hi>Teach us to number our dayes, aright, or well, or ſo as we ſhould.</hi> It's not every kind of numbering the Pſalmiſt prayes to be inſtructed in, but to number <hi>So;</hi> and this num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering, he holds forth to be a duty, wherein all are concerned, in that he prayes not for himſelf alone individually, but together with others, <hi>So teach us.</hi> And, which is yet more, he ſpeaks of it as a duty, wherein, when holy men have done their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, they will ſtill find themſelves defective. <hi>Moſes</hi> who <hi>was faithful in all the Houſe of God,</hi> doubtleſs made Conſcience of numbering his dayes, yet while he prayes, <hi>So teach us to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our dayes,</hi> he implicitely confeſſes himſelf to be defective in this matter, but withal, he ſees ſo much advantage in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of the duty, that he prayes for Grace to be helped, to go about it with more vigour; as knowing this would make him more and more to increaſe in Spiritual Wiſdom. And that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45736:4"/>is the other thing I ſaid was in the Words, namely, the Scope of <hi>Moſes</hi> in his Petition, or the benefit that will accrew by the right performance of the duty here ſpoken of; had we once learned aright to number our dayes, then, (and never till then) will we become wiſe to Salvation. <hi>So teach us to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our dayes, that we may apply our hearts unto wiſdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The only Head, to which I would ſpeak a little from the Words, ſhall be this. The right numbering of our dayes is a great and neceſſary duty, in order to the right performance whereof, we have need to be ſerious in imploring the Divine Aſſiſtance, and the rather, ſeeing it's a duty would make us wiſe unto Salvation. In purſuance of this, I would ſpeak a little to theſe three things. And firſt, I would more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly open the nature of this duty, <hi>So to number our dayes,</hi> by which the greatneſs and neceſſity of the work will appear. Secondly, I will demonſtrate the great need we have to implore the grace of God for the right performance of this duty. And Thirdly, I would give a touch of the benefit accrewing by it. It <hi>makes wiſe unto Salvation.</hi> Then I would make ſome Improvement of all, by way of Application.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt, the nature of the duty, <hi>So to number our days,</hi> take this <hi>Negative.</hi> This is not curiouſly to be enquiring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the period of our life, or manner of our death, making uſe of Genethliack Arts, or caſting Horoſcops. Some have been too curious that way, conſulting with Sorcerers, yea, with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and uſing unlawful methods; and it's an obſerve con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe, not more common then true, that ordinarly they make unhappy ends, as did <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate. This is not the numbering of our dayes, for which the Man of God here prayes. He did not prie into Secrets, which God thought not fit to reveal, it's enough for us that our times are in Gods hand, and that all the dayes of our appointed time, we wait till our change come. To open therefore, <hi>Poſitively</hi> a little of this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45736:4"/>Myſtery, I will endeavour to branch it forth into a few par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt</hi> then, when the Pſalmiſt prayes that <hi>God would teach him ſo to number his dayes,</hi> he prayes to be helped, to a due and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious conſideration of the frailty of his Nature, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.4. <hi>Lord make me to know mine end, and the meaſure of my dayes, what it is, that I may know how frail I am.</hi> O what a poor frail Creature is Man? The contexture of mans body, indeed is curious, <hi>Anda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis naturae miraculum,</hi> as one termed it, the Maſter-peice of bold Nature, or rather of Divine Providence, yet the Veſſels are ſo many, and the matter ſo thin and tender, the conveyances ſo ſubtile, that they are eaſily obſtructed by a little Sand, a little humor; Yea, ſometimes the whole Machine has been diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a little vapour. Neither is it ſo only with them, who have the more weak and creaſie bodies; experience having of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten made it appear, that bodies which ſeem'd more robuſt, as if they had been made of Cedar and Iron, yet have been very quickly ſhattered and blaſted; ſo true is that of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 40.6, 7. <hi>All fleſh is as graſs, and all the goodlineſs thereof as the flower of the field, the graſs withereth, the flower fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: becauſe the Spirit of the Lord hath blown upon it; ſurely the people is graſs.</hi> O how ſmall a thing will take away the life of man? a Gnat, a drop of a Gargariſm, yea, an Hair, and which may ſeem ſtrange, a Thought, an Apprehenſion, if it can but raiſe a violent Paſſion of Grief, Anger, yea of Joy. O how would the ſerious conſideration of this humble us, ſo as we ſhould neither be proud of Beauty, nor preſume of Strength.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> When he prayes to be taught, <hi>ſo to number his days,</hi> he prayes to be helped to a due conſideration of the ſhortneſs of his time, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.47. <hi>Remember how ſhort my time is,</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.5. <hi>Behold thou haſt made my dayes as an hand breadth, mine age is as nothing before</hi> thee. An hand breadth is a ſmall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45736:5"/>But as if that had been too little to ſhadow forth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tneſs of our time, its added, <hi>our age is as nothing before God,</hi> not ſo much as a drop to the Ocean, or a point to the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the vaſteſt Circle. In this Pſalm, the ordinary age of old men is reckoned to be <hi>ſeventy</hi> or <hi>eighty years;</hi> but what is that to infinite, immenſe eternity? It is ſaid, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. <hi>A thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years in thy ſight, are as yeſterday when it is paſt;</hi> and what is a day when it is paſt, but as nothing? In <hi>ver.</hi> 5. and 6. the ſhortneſſe of our time is compared <hi>to the ſtream of a floud when it is gone, to a ſleep when it is paſt, and to the graſs of the field, which in the morning groweth up and flouriſheth, and in the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is cut down and withereth.</hi> How little diſtance of time is betwixt its greenneſs and withering, its growing up and cutting down? What poor creatures are we? we grow up in the morning of our Childhood, we ſeem to flouriſh in the high noon-tide of our Adult-age, but then ſuddenly e're we be a ware, comes the declenſions of old age, wherein one infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity overtakes us after another, untill the ſickle of death cut us down root and branch. O what manner of perſons would we be <hi>in all holy converſation and godlineſs,</hi> were this duly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered?</p>
            <p>But thirdly, when he prayes <hi>to be taught to number his dayes,</hi> he prayes that he may be helped duly to conſider the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of his time here on earth: although it be ſaid, in ver. 10. of this Pſalm, that <hi>the years of a mans age are ſeventy or eighty,</hi> the meaning is not, that every one ſhall arrive to that age; nay, for one who cometh that length, many hundreds die with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that meaſure. Yea, the little time that we have, we have no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> certainty thereof; hence it is, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.1. <hi>Boaſt not thy ſelf of to morrow, thou knoweſt not what a day may bring forth.</hi> And <hi>Jam</hi> 4.13, 14. <hi>Go to now, ye that ſay to day or to morrow we will go to ſuch a city, and abide there for a year, and buy and ſell, and make gain, whereas thou knows not what ſhall be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45736:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>to morrow.</hi> For what is your life? it is even a vapour, that appeareth for a little time, and then vaniſheth away. We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make ſure reckoning of one day, one hour, one minute, more of our lives, what unexpected contingencies have men in greateſt health and ſecurity been ſurpriſed with? You may have heard how a Roman Conſul was brain'd by the fall of a Tile, as he rode in triumph; how <hi>Aeſchylus</hi> the Philoſoph was knock'd in the head to death, by the fall of a Tortoiſe from the claw of an Eagle; or how <hi>Anacreon</hi> the Poet was choaked by the kernel of a Raiſine, entring into the wrong paſſage of his throat. Doth not our Saviour bring in a man making ſuch a fooliſh reckoning with himſelf, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.19, 20. <hi>Soul, take thy caſe, thou haſt much goods laid up for thee for many years.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, <hi>God ſaid to him, thou fool, this night thy ſoul ſhall be required of thee, and then whoſe ſhall thoſe things be?</hi> Were the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of our time thought upon ſeriouſly, we would not delay repentance and preparation for death, nor make ſuch bold adventures upon ſin.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, when he prayes to be taught <hi>ſo to number his days,</hi> he prayes to be helped duly to conſider the certainty of death. Our time is uncertain, but death is moſt certain; there is a ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of heaven upon it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. <hi>Its appointed unto men once to die.</hi> Hence in ver. 3. of this Pſalm, it is ſaid, <hi>thou turneſt man to deſtruction, and ſayeſt, return ye children of men.</hi> Yea, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 89.48. the Pſalmiſt is peremptory, <hi>What man is he that liveth and ſhall not ſee death?</hi> I ſhall not here ſtand to debate, what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of thoſe who ſhall be alive at the laſt day, whether the ſentence of death ſhall be executed upon them. I know it is in reference to them the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51. <hi>We ſhall not all die, but we ſhall all be changed.</hi> And yet there be great Divines, both ancient and modern, among whom is the great <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> who hold that the Statute of death ſhall be executed on them alſo. And whereas it is ſaid, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>they ſhall not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45736:6"/>die,</hi> 
               <q>The meaning (ſay theſe Authors) only is, they ſhall not ſo die, as to remain under the power of death as others do, being preſently to be reſtored to life again.</q> However, all agree that a change is to paſs on them equivalent to death. Hence S. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38. to us the 39. <hi>Quid hic certum, niſi mors?</hi> what is certain in this world, but only death? <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras pecuniam? incertum eſt an proveniat:</hi> Expects thou to be rich? its uncertain if it ſhall be ſo. <hi>Speras filios? incertum an naſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantur:</hi> Hopes thou for children? its uncertain if thou ſhalt have any. <hi>Naſcuntur? incertum an vivant, an proficiant.</hi> Has thou children born? its uncertain whether they ſhall live; or if they live, whether they ſhall prove dutiful and towardly: and ſo he concludes, turn to what hand thou wilt, all is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, only it is moſt certain we muſt die. But alas! how few do practically believe this great truth, of the neceſſity and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of death? how ſew ſerious thoughts are ſpent upon it? It is ſaid of <hi>Caeſar Bergia,</hi> baſe Son to Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth, who deſigned to make himſelf Lord of <hi>Italy;</hi> in order to the obtaining which ambitious deſign, neither Father nor Son re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frained from any villany; but while one night they deſigned the poiſoning of others, the ſtroke, through the miſtake of the cup-bearer, falling on themſelves, of which the old man died inſtantly, the young man by ſtrong antidotes and the vigour of youth did live, yet was ſore ſickned, <hi>graviter decumbens,</hi> ſayes <hi>Guicciardin, lib.</hi> 6. In which ſickneſs, he confeſſed to ſome about him, he had foreſeen all the difficulties which ſtood in the way of his deſigns, and had conſidered how to remove them, yea and what to do in caſe of his Fathers death, whom he knew to be an old man; but upon his own death or ſickneſs, he had not ſo much as once reflected. How many do ſplit on the ſame rock? Hence is that unlucky Proverb in the mouths of many. <hi>I thought no more on ſuch a thing, then on the day of my death,</hi> A ſufficient evidence many meditate little on death, on the certainty thereof, and uncertainty of the time of it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:45736:6"/>
Fifthly, when the Pſalmiſt prayes to be taught to number his dayes, he prayes to be taught duly to consider the work he has to do in his dayes, that his work may not be undone, when his dayes are done; or that the work may not be then to do (which would have required his outmoſt ſolicitude all his dayes) when his dayes are drawing towards an end. And ſurely, great is the work which is committed to every one of us to do, faithfully to ſerve God in our Generation. To mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſie all our corrupt luſts <hi>to cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs both of the ſteſh and ſpirit,</hi> to be juſt and dutiful in all our relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>to work out our own ſalvation in fear and trembling,</hi> and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the ſalvation of others, ſo far as lies in our power, and to improve all our time, and all opportunity for the honour of God. May it not be ſaid, as one did in another caſe, <hi>Ars longa, vita brevis.</hi> How few alas! be there who ſeriouſly mind the work which God requireth of them? Elſe time would not be laviſhed in idle and unaccountable work, much leſs in that which is manifeſtly the work of the Fleſh, and the Devil.</p>
            <p>But Sixthly and laſtly, not to add more, when he prayes that God would teach him ſo to number his dayes, he prayes that he may be helped to consider, how much depends on the right or ill improvement of his time; Namely his bleſſed or miſerable eſtate to all eternity. As <hi>it is appointed once to die,</hi> ſo <hi>after death to come to judgement, Heb:</hi> 9: 27: And then <hi>to receive according to what we have done in the body, whether good or bad,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5: 10: They who obtain mercy to numbeer their dayes aright, how comfortable will it be to them, that they have done ſo, when they ſhall hear the Angel <hi>ſwear by him that lives for ever, that time ſhall be no more?</hi> But deſperat then will the ſtate of them be, who made no due improvement of their time. It's ſaid of <hi>Saul,</hi> though otherwiſe a valiant man, when he heard, that on the morrow he ſhould die, he was quite diſpirit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45736:7"/>1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.20. <hi>He fell ſtraight all along upon the ground, and was afraid;</hi> and no wonder, for the wrath of almighty God, and that to the outmoſt, will be the portion of ungodly ſinners to all eternity. Now as is ſaid in <hi>Verſe</hi> 11: of this <hi>Pſalm, Who knowes the power of his Wrath? as is his fear ſo is his wrath.</hi> We cannot have ſo deep apprehensions of it as it is.</p>
            <p>The branching forth of theſe few particulars, wherein the right numbering of our dayes does conſiſt, may ſufficiently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover that the duty is both great and neceſſary. Surely a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er work, then that of <hi>Pambo,</hi> which he was ſo many years in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning how to do according to the Word, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 39: 1: <hi>I ſaid I will take heed to my wayes, that I offend not with my tongue.</hi> That was but one branch of many, comprehended under this of number<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our dayes. As the Lord commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to number all the ſtations of the people of Iſrael in the Wilderneſs, <hi>Numb.</hi> 33: 2: as they are accordingly written down in that <hi>Chap.</hi> So the Lord would have us to number all the periods of our lives, duly to conſider our time paſt and to come, and what improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath been or ought to be made thereof; and ſo much of the firſt thing propoſed, the nature and neceſſity of this duty.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing propoſed was that we have need to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in imploring the Divine aſſiſtance, that we may be help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the right performance of this great duty, ſo did <hi>Moſes</hi> here; <hi>So teach us to number our dayes.</hi> So did <hi>David, Pſal:</hi> 39: 4: <hi>O Lord teach me to know mine end and the number of my dayes,</hi> the need of this might be made appear upon many accounts; As firſt, this is a great work, and therefore we have need of great aſſiſtance for it. A man may be able to number, how many hours, yea minuts, hath been ſince the Creation of the World, how many miles the circumference of the Earth doth contain, how many degrees the Pole is elevated above our Horizon, what is the poſition and diſtance of Stars, and a thouſand ſuch
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45736:7"/>like curioſities, and yet not know how to number his dayes aright, this is Divine Work; and therefore we have need to ſeek grace from above, to do it. As <hi>David</hi> in a like caſe, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 143: 10: <hi>Teach me to do thy will, for thou art my God.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, This is a work from which we are exceedingly averſe; people love not to think of death and of the end of their dayes, they will rather ſpend their thoughts upon any ſubject then that, yea ſome Princes have prohibited any to ſpeak of death within their Courts. But that could not ſtave off the approach of the King of Terrors. It only makes men more unfit to die. We have need therefore to implore the Divine aſſiſtance, that this averſion of our hearts from, and unfitneſs for, this work, may be done away. Thirdly, we have many diverſions from it, people are ſo taken up with fitting their Affairs, in numbering their Money, in fitting their accounts, in making their bargains, in doing their worldly buſineſs, that they hardly find time to number their dayes. There is need therefore of grace to help them to overcome theſe difficulties. Fourthly, this is a duty wherein the moſt eminent Saints ought ſtill to be making a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs. Have we come <hi>Davids</hi> or <hi>Moſes</hi>'s length in the work, there is yet a greater perfection to be endeavoured in this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Arithmetick, therefore there is ſtill need with this holy man in my Text, to be praying, <hi>So teach us to number our dayes, that we may apply our hearts unto wiſdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now only remains the third and laſt particular propounded in the Doctrine. That the right numbering of our dayes would be a choice mean to make us wiſe unto Salvation, ſo much the Text clearly holds forth, <hi>So teach us to number our dayes, that we may apply our hearts unto wiſdom.</hi> And in another Book of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Deut.</hi> 32: 29: <hi>O that they were wiſe, that they would remember their latter end,</hi> the neglect whereof gave occaſion to that grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous lamentation, <hi>Lam:</hi> 1: 9: <hi>She remembred not her latter end, therefore ſhe came down wonderfully.</hi> This briefly may appear
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45736:8"/>in theſe things. Firſt, The right numbering of our dayes would make us frugal of our time, and take heed how we beſtowed it, and believe me, that is an high point of wiſdom, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5: 15, 16: <hi>Walk circumſpectlie, not as fools, but as wiſe,</hi> how ſo? <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming the time.</hi> They who are careful to redeem time; ſhew themſelves indowed with the wiſdom which is from above. But ſecondly, they who rightly number their dayes, will ſurely mind the intereſt of their precious Souls. And that is wiſdom indeed, <hi>For what is a man profited,</hi> Math. 16: 26: <hi>if he gain the whole world, if he loſe his Soul?</hi> will not ſuch a man be found a fool at the latter end? Thirdly, they who rightly number their dayes, will be ſerious in the ſtudy of holineſs, and that is truly wiſdom, <hi>Deut:</hi> 4: 6. <hi>Keep my Commandments and do them, for this is your wiſdom in the fight of the Nations.</hi> And Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they who rightly number their dayes, will ſee ſo clearly, both the ſhortneſs and uncertainty of time; and conſequently the vanity of all the things thereof, that their great work will be to take hold of eternal life, which is to be wiſe for the time to come. And thus I have ſpoken a little to the three particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars propounded for opening of the Doctrine.</p>
            <p>I would now only (leſt I prove tedious) make two words of Improvement: And the firſt ſhall be of regrate; May there not becauſe to fear, that few among us have learned ſo to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berour dayes. Men may ſeem to be very perfect in other things, and yet very defective in this great point. Men may be very skilled Arithmeticians, in the moſt abſtruſe operations of <hi>Alge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra,</hi> and yet have no skill ſo to number their dayes: A man may be a skilled Aſtronomer, may underſtand the Theory of the Planets, and be able to calculate Eclipſes exactly, and yet alas! not have skill ſo to number his dayes. A man may be a skilled Merchant, perfect in book-holding, and the meaſures he ought to keep in Trading, and yet be a dunce in this Art of numbering his dayes. A man may be a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>illed N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>igator, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45736:8"/>able to reckon his Tides, and the declinations of the Magnet from the Pole, and yet have no skill to number his dayes. A man may be an able Stateſ-man, and know how to take his meaſures as to politique Affaires, and yet alas! be wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with this miſtery of numbering his dayes aright. A man may be an underſtanding Country-man, and know how to obſerve his ſeaſons, and yet not know how to number his days as he ſhould: But I muſt uſe this freedom, learn what we will, if we learn not to number our dayes, we are undone for ever. Yet that few have learned this Divine Art, might be made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by many ſad inſtances. As firſt, be there not many, who never once thought of numbering their dayes, never once con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered what this matter imported, or how defective they were therein. Muſt not ſuch be great ſtrangers to this miſtery. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, many make little account, how they laviſh their time in Carding, Dicing, Whoring, Debauching. O but the man that numbers his dayes, how precious will time be to him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring the ſtrict account he muſt give of every minut of it? A third inſtance may be, the little time people reſerve for Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Duties, ſome beſtow more time in looking on a Glaſs then on a Bible, ſome take more pleaſure in hunting a Partridge or an Hare, then in bowing their knees in Prayer, or in taking the Kingdom of Heaven by violence. Fourthly, there is little ſerious mourning for ill beſtowing of our time; and that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by our being ſo ready to repeat old ſins and turn back to folly, whereas they who are ſerious in numbering their dayes, will ſo bewail from their hearts the loſs of time, that they will carefully watch againſt the evils, by which they formerly, abuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their time. The fifth and laſt inſtance ſhall be, the little pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency we make in growing in grace and holineſs. This is the end why the Chriſtian numbers his dayes, that forgetting the things that are behind, he may reach forth to theſe that are before, and preſs toward the mark, the prize of the high cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45736:9"/>of God in Chriſt Jeſus. Theſe few things, alas! may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincingly demonſtrate, that many profeſſing Chriſtianity, have not learn'd this great art of numbering their dayes aright.</p>
            <p>The ſecond word of improvement ſhall be, by way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation. Let us all be exhorted more ſeriouſly to mind this great duty, <hi>of numbring our dayes:</hi> And to quicken us here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto let me point at a few things; as firſt, the faithful perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this duty is a good and ſolid Character of a ſerious and real Chriſtian; and on the contrary, the habitual neglect of it is an undoubted evidence of an ungodly ſoul. The Philoſoph made this a difference betwixt a man and a brute, that a man can number, and a brute cannot. Whatever be as to that, yet a ſound Believer hereby is ſolidly differenced, from a brutiſh formal Profeſſor; the true Believer has learned to number his dayes, not ſo the brutiſh hypocritical Profeſſors; The ſerious Chriſtian is held forth in ſcripture, as one that redeems his time, and how can this be without making right account, and numbring of our dayes? Secondly, if we number not our dayes, they will be numbered to our hands, and that in wrath: I remember to this purpoſe, what the finger which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> Dan. 5.5. wrote on the wall, <hi>ver.</hi> 25, 26. <hi>Mene mene,</hi> that is, <hi>God hath numbred thy Kingdom, and finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it.</hi> Will not we number our dayes, and redeem them; God will number them, and finiſh them in his wrath. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if now we will not number our dayes, we ſhall be made to number them to our ſorrow. O! how do we think do damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed reprobats in hell reflect upon their dayes here in a world? O! what dayes had I on earth (will the ſoul ſay) to ſeek God and to ſerve him? how many an opportunity had I both of receiving good from others, and doing good to others? But alas! I improved not theſe dayes of my viſitation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore am I now thrown to this place, and ſtate of torment for ever. Fourthly, if you will not number your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> will
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45736:9"/>get a harder ſum to number, and that to your everlaſting hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, to number the ages of Eternity; how long ſhall this flame devour? how long ſhall this worm gnaw? how many ages, yea millions, and millions of millions, of ages? and when the ſoul conſiders, theſe torments ſhall endure to eternity, ſhall ever be beginning, without any nearer approach to an end, this cannot but ſwallow up the wretch into horror and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration. Fifthly, Unſpeakable are the advantages may be had in being faithful in this great duty of numbring our dayes: I will only, for brevities ſake, hint at two; And firſt, this would be a powerful mean to wean our hearts from things of a preſent world, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29. <hi>This I ſay brethren, that the time is ſhort: It remains therefore, that they who have wives be as if they had none; they who weep, as if they weeped not; and they who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice, as if they rejoiced not; and they who uſe the world, as not abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it.</hi> O the bleſſed effect of numbering our dayes, which makes weeping as no weeping, and moderates our affections in all things, yea and engages the ſoul to the ſerious and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal ſtudy of mortification: Hence is that other word of that ſame Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.11. <hi>Knowing the time, that the night is far ſpent, it is therefore high time for to awake out of our ſleep, to caſt off the works of darkneſs, and to put on the armour of light.</hi> And then ſubjoins; <hi>Let us walk honeſtlie as in the day time, not in riot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drunkenneſs, not in chambering and wantonneſs, not in ſtrife and envying: But put ye on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> When a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death is paſt upon a moſt diſſolute man, he will not then readily debauch and whore; much more the man who by ſerious numbering of his dayes, is daily looking death in the face, cannot but mind mortifying works. And this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the other advantage flowing from this duty, It would put the ſoul upon a conſtant preparation for death, conſidering that it knows not, but that every hour may be its laſt hour; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, would make it walk by S. <hi>Bernards</hi> rule, <hi>Si mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urus eſſes,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45736:10"/>illud faceres?</hi> O my ſoul, were thou preſently by death, to take thy farewell from the body, wouldſt thou do ſuch or ſuch a thing, and this would make an abundant and comfortable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance unto our Lord his everlaſting Kingdom: The ſoul that is much in minding death and preparing for it, may ſay on better grounds then he did, <hi>the bitterneſs of death is paſt;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, they who neglect this great duty are oft overwhelmed at the approach of death; one crying out, O that I might live, though it were in a dungeon! another, Had I a world of wealth, I would give all for one inch of time; and another, <hi>Inducias Domine uſque mane,</hi> Spare, Lord, but one morning more. Might not theſe conſiderations quicken us to ſeriouſneſs in this great duty. What ſhall I add more? All the diſpenſations of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence, call aloud upon us to number our dayes; the revolutions of day and night, weeks, moneths and years; the birth of ſome, the death of others, our mercies, our rods, the voice of all is, that we ſhould <hi>ſo number our dayes, as to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our hearts unto wiſdom.</hi> God hath numbered the hairs of our heads by his Providence, and we ought to number our dayes for his ſervice. O that this Exhortation may be written, as with a pen of Iron and with the point of a Diamond, upon all our hearts!</p>
            <p>If then it be demanded, how we may be helped faithfully to perform this great duty of numbering our dayes; I only tender a few advices, and ſo ſhut up what I have to ſay on the Text.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, we would conſider the abſolute neceſſity of this duty; time and our dayes are a great Talent, for which a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere account muſt be given. Secondly, we would reflect, with all poſſible ſeriouſneſs, upon our failure in this matter, how much precious time we have loſt, how little of our work is done, though ſo much of our time be gone? The moral Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, when he had not improven a day to advantage, would
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45736:10"/>ſay, <hi>Ah! perdidi diem;</hi> Alas! I have loſt a day: what cauſe have we to lament the loſs of ſo many dayes? Thirdly, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider we, as this work is neceſſary, ſo alſo it is above our ſtrength; and therefore let us be fervent and frequent in prayer, for the quickening and ſtrengthening ſupplies of grace; <hi>So teach us to number our dayes, that we may apply our hearts unto wiſdom.</hi> Fourthly, let us ſupport our ſelves, that though the work be great and difficult, yet bleſſed be God, not impoſſible, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13. <hi>I can do all things through Chriſt that ſtrengtheneth me.</hi> Though we oft come ſhort in this duty, yet upon unfeigned re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, there is forgiveneſs with our Lord; the penitent thief miſpent many dayes, yet repenting ſincerely, found mercy. I ſpeak not this to encourage any in ſin, God forbid; but to encourage the worſt of ſinners unto repentance; if we repent as ſincerely as he did, we ſhall as aſſuredly find mercy. Though he lived a very little time after his converſion, yet he did much in it: So as to him, ſome way might be applyed, <hi>S. Hieroms</hi> word concerning <hi>Nebridius,</hi> Epiſt. 9. <hi>ad Salvinam, In brevi aetate multa complevit tempora;</hi> In a ſhort time he did the work of a long life. Fifthly, let us beware of theſe things that hinder the right per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this duty; particularly let us watch againſt the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the heart inordinately after the things of the world; that ſurely will divert from numbering of our dayes. Do not preſume, as that great man, who is ſaid to have taken for his Symbole a double headed Eagle, the one looking upward to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Heaven, the other looking downward toward the Earth; under which he wrote this Motto, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trumque;</hi> as if he could ſet his eye and heart upon both. But we would remember as is well obſerved, we have neither two heads nor two hearts, and though we have two eyes, yet I believe it is hard to look up and down with them at once. Sure I am, the Apoſtle puts theſe two in oppoſition, <hi>Col:</hi> 3: 2: <hi>The ſetting of our affections on things above, and not on things on earth.</hi> He who would num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45736:11"/>his dayes aright, would let but overly and mortified glances to the things of the world, the ſtrength of the heart muſt be ſet on things above. Sixthly and laſtly, we would ſequeſtrate a conſiderable portion of time dayly for this work, to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on the brevity and uncertainty of our Life, and of the great work God requires of us therein, and we would charge our hearts without delay to ſet about it. I have read how a godly Perſon gave a Prodigal a Gold-ring with a Deaths-head upon it, on condition, that he ſhould dayly, for the ſpace of ſeven dayes, look one hour thereupon, which proved the mean of his Converſion. Had the doing of this for ſeven dayes ſuch ſucceſs, how much more by the Lords bleſſing, were time ſequeſtrate dayly thorow the whole courſe of our lives for numbering of our dayes, might we hope for a bleſſed proficiency in this Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Art? So much have we ſpoken concerning this Text, as we judged your patience would bear at ſuch a time.</p>
            <p>YOu expect, I know, before I cloſe, that ſomething beſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Honourable Perſon, whoſe Funerals we now Celebrate. And here I confeſs vvere a large Field, vvere I fitted or diſpoſed for a Panegyrick: Nor is there want of great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents in ſuch caſes from <hi>Nazianzen, Ambroſe,</hi> and many others, both ancient and modern. Nor can it be denyed, but that the doing juſtice to the memory of deſerving perſons, may excite the living to trace the footſteps of the virtues of the dead. Yet, I not being accuſtomed to ſuch Diſcourſes, and having a through averſion of what may ſavour of flattery, I hope therefore I shall be the more eaſily excuſed, if I be the more ſparing on this head.</p>
            <p>Though this worthy Gentleman did live much of his time abroad, out of his Native Country, yet the fame both of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Merit, did overſpread theſe three Kingdoms, yea, and did reach to other Nations alſo. The antiquity of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45736:11"/>Family of <hi>Doors</hi> is beyond diſpute. The Stock where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was, an immediat Son of the Great <hi>Thane of Cowy and Doors,</hi> (for ſo I underſtand he was deſigned) upwards of three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years ago, at the ſame time that another Son of the ſame Great <hi>Thane,</hi> married the noble Heretrix of <hi>Philorth.</hi> The Eſtate poſſeſt by the <hi>Thane</hi> was very vaſt about theſe <hi>Grampian Mountains:</hi> and of him, and of the great Lord <hi>Fraiſer</hi> in the South, two Families of the ſame name, of ſo great Antiquity, that it is hard to account, which did come of the other; yet of theſe two, many noble Families of this Kingdom acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge themſelves to be deſcended, and therefore have the <hi>Frai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers</hi> Arms quartered with their own. But I confeſs, I am not Herauld enough to dilate upon this Subject.</p>
            <p>Should any ſay to me with him in the Poet,
<q>
                  <l>Et Genus, &amp; Proavus, &amp; quae non fecimus ipſi</l>
                  <l>Vix ea noſtra voco—</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Though none, I hope, will deny a due eſteem to an Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Deſcent, unleſs he be of a levelling Principle: Yea, the holy Scripture ſpeaks honourably of the ſons of Nobles, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ,</hi> 10.17. Yet, I have this to add, that beſides this Gentlemans honourable deſcent, he was a man of eminent perſonal worth and merit: whereof take this one inſtance among many, that when this family of <hi>Doores</hi> had lately ſuffered an eclipſe, as ancient Houſes have their viciſſitudes, he by his virtue and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry recovered it from a collapſed condition. He might, without all peradventure, have made comfortable Purchaſes in the pleaſant places of <hi>England;</hi> yet, ſuch was his love to his native Country, and to this ancient Seat of his Anceſtors, that he chooſed rather to make an Atchievment here. And now, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing provided his other worthy and well-deſerving Children of riper years, hath tranſmitted this old Heretage of his Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, with all its Dignities, to his hopeful Son here preſent, who by the Mother (a Lady of great Virtue) is deſcended of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45736:12"/>honourable Name of <hi>Caries</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> a Family which bears as noble marks of Honour and ancient Pedegree, as moſt of the Nobleſt Families in that Kingdom. This his youngeſt Son, he ſent hither to be educated, and who, I truſt, by the mercy of God, ſhall inherit many of the Virtues of his Predeceſſors. So that he had both the Dignity of an honourable Deſcent, and likewiſe (which in conjunction with the former, I believe will be highly eſteemed by all) of a juſt and virtuous Acquiſition.</p>
            <p>This may ſeem much; yet I ſee an Ocean before me, on which I dare hardly adventure: But one thing I cannot let paſſe, his unſtained Loyalty to his Soveraign, in times of great trouble and temptation. He was fourty years and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a Courtier, in the Reign of two Kings, and beheld with ſorrowful eyes, the moſt diſmal convulſions which ever theſe Kingdoms did ſuffer; yet was he never ſtained with a blot of diſloyalty.</p>
            <p>He was educated a Schollar at <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> the time when his Family fell low: And after he had ſpent ſome years in his youth over Seas, in purſuance of his Studies, and had been Graduated Doctor of Medicine at <hi>Piemont,</hi> he was ſo much noticed in the Court of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> at his return, for his Learning and Skill in that excellent Faculty which he did profeſs, that in the year, 1639. he was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Phyſician in ordinary to King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt of glorious Memory, and ſerved his Majeſty faithfully in Peace and War, both in his Profeſſion and other eminent Services, untill the evils of the time encreaſing, he was by ſpecial order from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, ſent to attend the Prince then in <hi>Flanders,</hi> with whom he continued doing many conſiderable ſervices, untill our Dread Soveraign who now reigns, and whom Almighty God long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, came to <hi>Scotland</hi> in the year, 1650.</p>
            <p>And his Majeſty again departing beyond Seas, the confuſions of the Times ſtill prevailing, he was among the firſt who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired to his Majeſty, leaving Family and Employment (which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45736:12"/>he might have had very conſiderable) eſteemed it his greateſt Honour and Advantage to ſuffer hardſhips in ſerving his Prince. In conſideration of this conſtant Fidelity and Loyalty, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of himſelf to many hazards in his Princes Service, It pleaſed his Gracious Majeſty, at his happy Reſtauration, to ſettle him as Principal Phyſician, to have the care and inſpection of his Royal Perſon. In this great Truſt he continued untill his death; and ſo great was the confidence his Majeſty had, both of his Skill and Faithfulneſs, that he would not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily take Phyſick without him. Amongſt the many marks of his Princes favour, the Honour of Baronet was confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon him, beſides the Places and Preferments ſettled on his Lady and Children: Nay, ſo gracious a Prince did he ſerve, that his favour did not expire with the life of his faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; And therefore gave order to tranſmit his Remains in one of his Royal Ships unto <hi>Scotland,</hi> to be buried in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre of his Fathers.</p>
            <p>It would take a Volume to recount all the Offices of kindneſs he did to his Country-men by his friendſhip, by his skill in Medicine, and when occaſion did require, by his Purſe alſo. A man he was of great Generoſity, Integrity, and a moſt faithful and faſt Friend. Theſe things could not but purchaſe to him admirable repute. Hence it was, that when within theſe few years, he made a viſit to his Native Country, and lived ſome Months here at <hi>Doores,</hi> a great confluence of perſons of eminent quality reſorted hither to pay their reſpects to him, all whom he entertained nobly; And yet diſdained not to give his moſt Judicious Conſultations to multitudes of Diſeaſed Perſons, who alſo flocked to him from all quarters, for Cure of obſtinate Maladies, which had given defiance to the skill of other Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, all which he did <hi>Gratis;</hi> Nor did his Country-men more rejoyce in his Converſe among them, in that little interval, then he was longed for again at Court, as was manifeſt by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45736:13"/>Letters he receiv'd at the time, from great Perſons at Court, and by his gracious Reception from his Soveraign at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</p>
            <p>Had any of the Divines who attended him in his Sickneſs, been performing this laſt Office to him, I doubt not, but they could have given an account of his Religious Deportment at Death; all who knew him here will witneſs, to his Temperance and Sobriety, his conſtant adherence to the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> was manifeſt to all. It was by his Charity and Supply, with the concurrence of his Servants, thorow his direction, and the influence, aſſiſtance and conſiderable expence of a moſt deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Friend and Relation of his, that the Pious Work of the Bridge of <hi>Dy</hi> (towards which a ſum of Money was Mortified by a Reverend Miniſter, though that without the aſſiſtance foreſaid could never have done it) was promoved and brought to the finiſhing Cubit. And it is by his means that this old Place and Church (where his Fathers did Worſhip God) is now repaired, or rather re-builded. There is one inſtance more of his Piety, which if I ſhould forget, I ſhould be unjuſt to his memory: He was pleaſed to favour me with ſome Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, in reference to his beloved Son; and I muſt declare, that ſo far as I remember, he never did omit in any of them, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, that his Son might be religiouſly educated in the fear of the Lord, ſolemnly proteſting, <hi>He would rather have him good than great,</hi> Theſe were his own expreſſions, whereof I found my ſelf often obliged to put his hopeful Son in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berance.</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:45736:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
